## Samson Koelle

Seattle, WA — sjkoelle@gmail.com — sjkoelle.github.io

I am a researcher and engineer working on artificial intelligence, interpretable machine learning, and computational biology. I have published several first author machine learning papers and products I have worked on have been used by millions of people.

### Skills

Methods: Python PyTorch GitHub Modeling Kubernetes AWS

Domains: Generative AI TTS Neuro. Unsup. learning Mol. dynamics Hematology

## Experience

Uberduck, Inc. Cofounder/Head of ML Seattle, WA 08/2021 - 03/2024

AI science and engineering for text-to-speech; headed R&D (up to 3 person team) for startup

Allen Institute for Brain Science Contractor Seattle, WA 01/2020 – 12/2020

Data science for brain connectivity; published first author paper

Amazon SCOT Forecasting Sci. Research Intern Seattle, WA 06/2017 - 09/2017

AI science for sales forecasting; online training of fine-tuned models

Fred Hutchinson Graduate assistant Seattle, WA 09/2015 – 06/2017

Data science for single cell RNA sequencing

Nat. Heart, Lung, & Blood Inst. IRTA Bethesda, MD 07/2013 - 05/2015

Data and experimental science for hematopoietic stem cells; published first author paper

#### Education

Y Combinator San Francisco, CA 01/2022 - 03/2022

Ph.D. Statistics University of Washington, Seattle, WA 09/2015 - 03/2022

Thesis: Geometric algorithms for interpretable manifold learning.

Committee: Marina Meila (advisor), Yen-Chi Chen, Zaid Harchaoui, John Lee

**B.A. Mathematics** Columbia University, New York, NY 09/2009 – 05/2013

#### References

Zach Ocean Uberduck, Inc. z@uberduck.ai

Marina MeilaUniversity of Washington Department of Statisticsmmp@uw.eduStefan MihalasAllen Institute for Brain Sciencestefanm@alleninstitute.org

Cynthia Dunbar National Heart Lung and Blood Institute dunbarc@nhlbi.nih.gov

#### **Publications**

Koelle, Samson J et al. (2024). "Consistency of Dictionary-Based Manifold Learning". In: *Proceedings of The 27th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*. Ed. by Sanjoy Dasgupta et al. Vol. 238. Proceedings of Machine Learning Research. PMLR, pp. 4348–4356.

Koelle, Samson et al. (Dec. 2023). "Modeling the cell-type-specific mesoscale murine connectome with anterograde tracing experiments". en. In: *Netw Neurosci* 7.4, pp. 1497–1512.

Koelle, Samson (2022). "Geometric Algorithms for Interpretable Manifold Learning". en. PhD thesis. Ann Arbor, United States: University of Washington.

Koelle, Samson J et al. (2022). "Manifold Coordinates with Physical Meaning". In: *J. Mach. Learn. Res.* 23.133, pp. 1–57.

- Buenfil, James et al. (2021). "Tangent Space Least Adaptive Clustering". en. In: 2021 ICML Unsupervised Learning for Reinforcement Learning Workshop.
- Espinoza, Diego A et al. (Apr. 2021). "Interrogation of clonal tracking data using barcodetrackR". en. In: Nat Comput Sci 1.4, pp. 280–289.
- Koelle, Samson and Zhang, Hanyu and Meila, Marina and Chen, Yu-Chia (2019). "Manifold coordinates with physical meaning". In: NeuRIPs Machine Learning for Physical Sciences Workshop.
- Xu, Jason et al. (2019). "Statistical inference for partially observed branching processes with application to cell lineage tracking of in vivo hematopoiesis". In: *Ann. Appl. Stat.* 13.4, pp. 2091–2119.
- Meila, Marina et al. (Nov. 2018). "A regression approach for explaining manifold embedding coordinates".
- Paulson, K G et al. (Sept. 2018). "Acquired cancer resistance to combination immunotherapy from transcriptional loss of class I HLA". en. In: *Nat. Commun.* 9.1, p. 3868.
- Wu, Chuanfeng et al. (Nov. 2018a). "Clonal expansion and compartmentalized maintenance of rhesus macaque NK cell subsets". en. In: Sci Immunol 3.29.
- Wu, Chuanfeng et al. (Jan. 2018b). "Geographic clonal tracking in macaques provides insights into HSPC migration and differentiation". en. In: *J. Exp. Med.* 215.1, pp. 217–232.
- Yabe, Idalia M et al. (Dec. 2018). "Barcoding of Macaque Hematopoietic Stem and Progenitor Cells: A Robust Platform to Assess Vector Genotoxicity". en. In: *Mol Ther Methods Clin Dev* 11, pp. 143–154.
- Yu, Kyung-Rok et al. (Mar. 2018). "The impact of aging on primate hematopoiesis as interrogated by clonal tracking". en. In: *Blood* 131.11, pp. 1195–1205.
- Koelle, Samson J et al. (Mar. 2017). "Quantitative stability of hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell clonal output in rhesus macaques receiving transplants". en. In: *Blood* 129.11, pp. 1448–1457.
- Wu, Chuanfeng et al. (Apr. 2014). "Clonal tracking of rhesus macaque hematopoiesis highlights a distinct lineage origin for natural killer cells". In: Cell Stem Cell 14.4, pp. 486–499.

#### Service

Reviewer	AISTAT	2023
Reviewer	m JMLR	2021
Reviewer	UAI	2020-2021
Organizer	UW Geometric Data Analysis reading group (uwgeometry.github.io)	2017-2021

#### Software

https://github.com/uberduck-ai/uberduck-ml-dev	Audio ML models	378  stars
https://github.com/sjkoelle/montlake	Geometric data analysis	11 stars

## Support/Awards

IPAM ML for Physics & the Physics of Learning	UCLA	2019
IGERT Big Data Fellowship	University of Washington	2017-2019
Chateaubriand Fellowship	Embassy of France	2016
GRFP Honorable Mention	NSF	2016

# Presentations

Manifold Coord. w/ Phys. Meaning	ITA Workshop	San Diego, CA	2/2020
Manifold Coord. w/ Phys. Meaning	NeuRIPs ML4PhysicalSci	Vancouver, CA	12/2019
Manifold Coord. w/ Phys. Meaning	BIDS	Berkley, CA	12/2019
Manifold Coord. w/ Phys. Meaning	UCLA IPAM	Los Angeles, CA	9/2019
Manifold Coord. w/ Phys. Meaning	Moore Sloan Foundation	Park City, Utah	9/2019
Wasserstein Distance Optimization	JSM	Baltimore, MD	7/2017
Stability of Hematopoiesis	ASH	San Francisco, CA	12/2014